Vance Randolph collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Vance Randolph collection 1941-1972 1941-1943
AFC 1941/001
Randolph, Vance, 1892-1980
18,216 items
25 boxes
273 folders
255 sound discs: analog; various sizes, 16 in. and smaller
1 sound tape reel; 5 in.
167 photographic prints
8 photographic negatives
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Field recordings, photographs, and manuscripts documenting Ozark Mountains folksong, folklife, and local history from 1941 to 1972, collected by Vance Randolph.
Provenance
Sound recordings: Accessioned, 1941-1942.
Manuscripts and photographs: Vance Randolph; Donation; 1972.
Accrual: Rayna Green; Donation; 2021.
The Vance Randolph collection began with the field recordings that the Archive of American Folk Song commissioned Randolph to make in 1941 and 1942. Randolph donated his personal papers to the Library of Congress in 1972; the two accessions have been combined. A 2021 accrual has been added.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Materials in the Prints and Photographs Division collection Photographs of Folk Musicians in Arkansas and Missouri (Lot 5580) may have been transferred from the present collection (AFC 1941/001) in 1948.
Related Material
The Manuscript Division has a collection entitled Vance Randolph Book Typescripts, 1947-1953 (MMC-3244), which contains the typescripts of Ozark Superstitions, We Always Lie to Strangers, Who Blowed Up the Church House?, and Down in the Holler with handwritten corrections.
The Music Division has a 1949 manuscript and microfilm copy of "Unprintable" Songs and Other Folklore Materials from the Ozarks [M1629.R23 U5 (Case)] by Vance Randolph.
The Prints and Photographs Division holds 40 photographs in the collection Photographs of Folk Musicians in Arkansas and Missouri (Lot 5580) from the 1941-1942 field trips.
Access and Restrictions
The Vance Randolph collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Vance Randolph was a self-educated folklorist who made a living as a professional writer. Born in Pittsburg, Kansas, in 1892, he was educated as a scientist: as an undergraduate, he studied biology, and then in graduate school at Clark University, in psychology. As a graduate student, Randolph began to earn money by coaching students and ghostwriting. He then moved to the Ozark Mountains, where he lived for the remainder of his life. He was married twice, the first marriage lasting through the 1930s. In 1962 he married Mary Celestia Parler, a professor of English at the University of Arkansas and an active member of the folklore community, in Fayetteville, Arkansas.
In the 1920s, Randolph began writing about the Ozark folklore he was collecting. He published several articles on dialect, folk belief, and recreation. His first books of folklore scholarship, The Ozarks and Ozark Mountain Folks, were published in the 1930s. He went on to publish Ozark Folksongs (4 vols., 1946-50) and Ozark Superstitions (1947). In the 1950s, he published four collections of folktales and a book about language in the Ozarks. His other major publications include Ozark Folklores: A Bibliography (1972), Pissing in the Snow and other Ozark Folktales (1976), and Unprintable Ozark Folksongs and Folklore (1992). In 1978 Randolph was elected as a Fellow of the American Folklore Society, crowning a distinguished career with this formal professional honor.
Scope and Content
The Vance Randolph collection had its beginnings in the early 1940s with fieldwork conducted by the well-known amateur Ozark folklorist Vance Randolph. In February 1941, Alan Lomax, then head of the Archive of American Folk Song at the Library of Congress, wrote to Vance Randolph, asking if he would consider making field recordings in the Ozarks. Randolph accepted the request and began to conduct fieldwork with recording equipment and film supplied by the Archive. By the end of 1942, he had collected more than 870 selections on 198 discs (either aluminum or glass-based and lacquer) for the Library of Congress and photographs of people he recorded. Randolph used much of the material he collected in his book Ozark Folksongs, while the Archive included selections from these field recordings on the following releases: L-12, Anglo-American Songs and Ballads; L-14, Anglo-American Songs and Ballads; L-20, Anglo-American Songs and Ballads; L-30, Songs of the Mormons and Songs of the West (this release includes Randolph himself singing Starving to Death on a Government Claim ); L-61, Railroad Songs and Ballads; and L-62, American Fiddle Tunes.
In addition to the field recordings mentioned above, the Vance Randolph collection contains the author's personal papers, which he donated to the Library of Congress in 1972. The papers consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic notes, field notes, research notes, photographic prints, manuscripts, maps, typescripts, telegrams and correspondence, dating from the first decade of the twentieth century to the 1960s.
Arrangement
The Vance Randolph collection has been organized into four series:
Series 1: Manuscript Materials
Series 2: Sound Recordings
Series 3: Graphic Materials
Series 4: 2021 Accrual
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bilyeu, Willie, 1902-1973; Campbell, Booth; Carlisle, Irene Jones; Denoon, Jimmy, 1921-1978; Hammontree, Doney; Ingenthron, Charles; Jordan, Lon; McCord, May K.; Randolph, Vance, 1892-1980; Randolph, Vance, 1892-1980--Correspondence.; Randolph, Vance, 1892-1980--Ethnomusicological collections.; Read, Lessie Stringfellow, 1891-1971; Starr, Belle, 1848-1889.; Tuttle, Mildred
Organizations
Archive of Folk Song (U.S.)
Subjects
Ballads, English--Ozark Mountains Region.; Children's songs, English--Ozark Mountains Region.; English language--Dialects--Ozark Mountains Region.; Fiddle tunes--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folk dance music--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folk festivals--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folk literature--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folk music--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folk songs, English--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folklore--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folklorists--Ozark Mountains Region.; Folklorists--United States--Correspondence.; Games--Ozark Mountains Region.; Hymns, English--Ozark Mountains Region.; Material culture--Ozark Mountains Region.; Old-time music--Ozark Mountains Region.; Rites and ceremonies--Ozark Mountains Region.; Shape-note singing--Ozark Mountains Region.; Singing games--Ozark Mountains Region.; Storytelling--Ozark Mountains Region.; Superstition--Ozark Mountains Region.; Tales--Ozark Mountains Region.; Tall tales.; Traditional medicine--Ozark Mountains Region.
Places
Arkansas--Folklore.; Missouri--Folklore.; Oklahoma--Folklore.; Ozark Mountains--History, Local.; Ozark Mountains--Religious life and customs.; Ozark Mountains--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Clippings.; Correspondence.; Field recordings.; Lecture notes.; Manuscripts.; Photographic prints.; Sound recordings.
Collection Concordance by Format
Manuscript Materials
261 folders Boxes 1-20, 23-24
Sound Recordings
191 12-inch glass-based acetate discs AFS 5236-5425 in M/B/RS. AFS 5270, 5320, 5341, 5425 missing; 5300 broken (Preservation tapes LWO 3493, reels 14-26)
56 16-inch, 12-inch, 10-inch glass-based acetate discs, 8-inch aluminum-based acetate discs AFS 6397-6464 in M/B/RS. AFS 6398 missing; 6400 scratched; 6463 badly broken. AFS 6397 = Preservation tapes LWO 3493, reel 42B; AFS 6399 = Preservation tapes LWO 4872 reel 412A; AFS 6400-6463 = Preservtion tapes LWO 3493, reel 42B-46A; AFS 6464 = Preservation tapes LWO 4872 reel 412A
8 12-inch glass-based acetate discs AFS 6897-6904 in M/B/RS. AFS 6897 damaged; 6900 broken = Preservation tapes LWO 3493, reels 56-57
1 5-inch reel-to-reel tape "Some Talk About Belle Starr" in Box 21
Graphic Materials
213 photographs, including 164 prints, 8 negatives, and 41 photocopied reproductions In folders 263-79, Boxes 21-22; also in subject file folders 35, 53, 74, 168, 173
Electronic Media
2 3.5-inch computer diskettes Folder 1a in Box 1 contains this collection guide, attachments, finding aid tagged with EAD, and 2 diskettes
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscript Materials
  - Administrative Files
    - Collection guide., Contains the collection guide and three appendices listing reprinted articles and book reviews. (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    - Log of visual images., Table A describes the photoprints and negatives housed in the AFC 1941/001 collection; Table B describes the photographs housed in the Prints and Photographs Division as Lot 5580. Descriptions include the photograph number, subject, location, setting, and related photographs. (Box 1, Folder 1b)
    - The Vance Randolph collection: Ozark Folk Music., Contains photocopies of the Archive's card catalog entries, and the song lists, performer, place, and recording information for the field recordings made by Randolph for the Library of Congress. It includes photocopies of catalog cards for 5236 A-5270 B3, an annotated manuscript of catalog entries for 5271 A1-5425 B3, an annotated list of fiddle tunes played by Lon Jordan (5314-5317, 5319-5326, 5376-5379, 5401-5402, 5404-5405), and two lists of fiddle tunes played by Bill Bilyeu (6897 A1-6904 B3). (Box 1, Folder 1c)
  - Subject Files
    - Ancestors., Contains typed and handwritten notes about Vance Randolph's family history. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Arthur Aull., Contains newspaper clippings and handwritten notes concerning the Ozark newspaperman Arthur Aull. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Beat Texas., Contains newspaper clippings and correspondence relating to football. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Thomas Hart Benton., Contains newspaper clippings concerning artist Thomas Hart Benton. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bibliography (Photocopy)., Contains a chronological bibliography of Vance Randolph's published articles, compiled by Randolph. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bibliography (Original). (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Booze, etc. H-V stuff., Contains newspaper clippings and handwritten and typed notes dealing with alcoholism, homosexuality, insomnia, and smoking. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Butterfly Still Lives.", Contains a 2-page typed manuscript dealing with Vance Randolph's childhood. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cavemen of the Ozarks., Contains newspaper clippings and a typed manuscript dealing with prehistoric settlements in the Ozarks. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Children's games. Folder 1 of 2., Contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, handwritten and typed notes, and a reprint of "Ozark Mountain Party-Games" ( Journal of American Folklore 1936). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Children's games. Folder 2 of 2., Contains handwritten notes. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Children's rhymes. Folder 1 of 2., Contains a reprint of "Children's Rhymes from Missouri" ( Journal of American Folklore 1950), newspaper clippings, correspondence, and typed and handwritten notes. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Children's rhymes. Folder 2 of 2., Contains typed notes. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - College such as it was., Contains newspaper clippings and handwritten notes dealing with the Kansas State College of Pittsburgh. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Concrete Cadillac., Contains typed and handwritten notes, and a copy of The Oregon Folklore Bulletin dealing with the urban tale known as "The Concrete Cadillac." Also contains a Günther Grass passage, translation, and notes. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Covered wagon., Contains typed and handwritten notes dealing with Vance Randolph's trip through the Ozarks in a covered wagon. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Cuss words., Contains newspaper clippings, typed and handwritten notes dealing with Ozark profanities. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Dance calls. Folder 1 of 2., Contains newspaper clippings; typed and handwritten notes dealing with folk dancing. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Dance calls. Folder 2 of 2., Contains typed and handwritten notes. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Dances and fiddle tunes. Folder 1 of 1., Contains newspaper clippings; typed and handwritten notes dealing with folk dancing and fiddle playing. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Dances and fiddle tunes. Folder 2 of 2., Contains typed and handwritten notes. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Pea Ridge" Day., Contains newspaper clippings; typed and handwritten notes dealing with the professional baseball player Henry Clyde "Pea Ridge" Day. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Dialect., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes. Includes the following subjects: advertisements, disputes, word list. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Dialect articles., Contains newspaper clippings and notes on articles about dialect. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Dialect correspondence., Contains correspondence dealing with Ozark dialect, including letters from E.H. Criswell, Elsie and Louis Freund, Herbert Halpert, Louise Pound, Rose Spaulding, and George P. Wilson. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Dialect notes. Folder 1 of 2., Contains index cards and typed notes in sequential order. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Dialect notes. Folder 2 of 2., Contains typed and handwritten notes. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - J. Frank Dobie., Contains a newspaper clipping and index card dealing with the author J. Frank Dobie. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Dulcimer, banjo, guitar., Contains newspaper clippings, articles, and typed notes dealing with folk instruments. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Maude Duncan., Contains newspaper clippings dealing with newspaperwoman Maude Duncan. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Fake antiques., Contains typed and handwritten notes; articles. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Fiddle. Folder 1 of 2., Contains typed and handwritten notes and newspaper clippings about tuning and the manner of playing. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Fiddle. Folder 2 of 2., Contains typed and handwritten notes about the differences between violin and fiddle playing. Includes a paginated manuscript. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Fiddle construction., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, dealing with the construction of fiddles. Also contains an annotated photoprint of a man playing a "mussel-shell" fiddle, along with the corresponding negative. Includes notes on snake rattles, the three-string fiddle, and the gourd fiddle. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Ozark fiddle tunes., Contains correspondence, articles, and typed and handwritten notes. Also contains a reprint copy of Vance Randolph's article "The Names of Ozark Fiddle Tunes" ( Midwest Folklore 1954). (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - John Gould Fletcher., Contains handwritten and typed notes, correspondence, newspaper clippings dealing with the poet John Gould Fletcher and the Ozark Folklore Society. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Folk belief and superstition. Folder 1 of 6., Contains newspaper clippings and typed and handwritten notes. Includes articles by Vance Randolph. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Folk belief and superstition. Folder 2 of 6., Contains typed and handwritten notes, newspaper clippings, correspondence, and a term paper. Topics included: fishing and folk medicine. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Folk belief and superstition. Folder 3 of 6., Contains newspaper clippings and a term paper. Topics included: lead miners and miscellaneous articles. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Folk belief and superstition. Folder 4 of 6., Contains newspaper clippings, typed and handwritten notes, and correspondence. Includes: miscellaneous notes and "Our Town" column. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Folk belief and superstition. Folder 5 of 6., Contains newspaper clippings, brochures, and typed and handwritten notes. Includes: pamphlets, and advertisements. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Folk belief and superstition. Folder 6 of 6., Contains newspaper clippings, typed and handwritten notes, and correspondence. Topics include: weatherlore. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Folk belief and superstition: Correspondence., Contains letters and newspaper clippings. Includes correspondence with Charles M. Bogert, William Edward Cox, Wayland D. Hand, Mrs. Mahnkey, May Kennedy McCord, in re. Albert Pike, Rose Spaulding, Barre Toelken, and Ruth Tyler; also includes miscellaneous correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Folk festivals. Folder 1 of 5., Contains newspaper clippings, festival programs, correspondence, and typed and handwritten notes. Includes: Arkansas Folklore Society, American Folklore Society, American Anthropology Associations, Florida Folk Festival, National Folk Camp, and other associations. (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Folk festivals. Folder 2 of 5., Contains newspaper clippings, festival programs, correspondence, and typed and handwritten notes. Includes: National Folk Festival in Cleveland (1946), St. Louis (1948-54). (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Folk festivals. Folder 3 of 5., Contains newspaper clippings, festival programs, correspondence, and typed and handwritten notes. Includes: National Folk Festival in Oklahoma City (1957), Ozark Folk Festival in Rolla, MO (1935), Eureka Springs (1949-53). (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Folk festivals. Folder 4 of 5., Contains newspaper clippings, festival programs, correspondence, and typed and handwritten notes. Includes: Ozark Folk Festival in Eureka Springs (1954-65). (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Folk festivals. Folder 5 of 5., Contains assorted newspaper clippings. (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Folklore and history., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, dealing with folklore studies in academia and the relationship between folklore and history. (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Folksong. Folder 1 of 2., Contains correspondence, typed and handwritten notes, and song transcriptions. (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Folksong. Folder 2 of 2., Contains typed and handwritten notes. (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Folksong articles., Contains assorted newspaper clippings about folksong, articles by Vance Randolph, John Gould Fletcher, and Sidney Robertson Cowell and Henry Cowell, and a 1939 photograph of Sidney Robertson Cowell. (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Folksong letters. Folder 1 of 3. 1927-40., Contains correspondence to and from Vance Randolph dealing with his experiences collecting folksongs in the Ozarks. Correspondents include: Louise Pound, Franz Boas, Harvard University Press, George Lyman Kittredge, Dororthy Scarborough, "The Twelve Apostles," and "The Mermaid." (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Folksong letters. Folder 2 of 3. 1941-42 (June)., Correspondents include: The Library of Congress, Alan Lomax, Edward Water, Sidney Robertson Cowell, Thomas Benton, John Stilley, John Robert Moore (re. the integrity of Child 218), and the Music Library Association. (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Folksong letters. Folder 3 of 3. 1942 (August)-57., Correspondents includs: The Library of Congress, B.A. Botkin, Wayland D. Hand, Mildred McMullen Green, Ruth Crawford Seeger, and Evelyn K. Wells. (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Folksong: "Songs Collected in the Ozark Mountains.", Contains a list of folksongs compiled by Vance Randolph. (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Fox hunting. Folder 1 of 2., Contains newspaper clippings, magazine clippings, and typed and handwritten notes. (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Fox hunting. Folder 2 of 2., Contains newspaper clippings. (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Connie Franklin., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, dealing the alleged murder of Connie Franklin. (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Girard Airship., Contains a newspaper clipping dealing with the first airplane factory and flying school in Kansas. (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Gone Are the Days., Contains one copy of Gone Are the Days: A Book of Boyhood Memories, written by L.J. Hedgecock. (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - "A Green Fork Turns to Water.", Contains a newspaper clipping entitled "A Green Fork Turns to Water," which deals with water witches. (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Groundhog., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, dealing with groundhogs and woodchucks. (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Guns and gunplay., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, and correspondence. (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Louis Hanecke., Contains typed and handwritten notes dealing with Louis Hanecke, owner of the Allred Hotel in Carroll County. (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - The healing waters., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, dealing with mineral water and spring water in the Ozarks. (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Hidden treasure. Folder 1 of 3., Contains correspondence, Exciting Adventures Along the Indian Frontier by W.R. Draper, and typed and handwritten notes. (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Hidden treasure. Folder 2 of 3., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes. (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Hidden treasure. Folder 3 of 3., Contains newspaper clippings. (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Hog calling., Contains two typewritten pages of notes. (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Hollywood., Contains newspaper and magazine clippings dealing with Hollywood's treatment of writers. (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Introduction., Contains a typescript of a title page and notes for the preface of Ozark Folklore: Selected Papers of Vance Randolph, arranged and edited by Mary Celestia Parler. (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Jacob's Cavern. Folder 1 of 3., Contains manuscript articles by Vance Randolph and Vernon C. Allison and photographs of Jacob's Cavern, Missouri. (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Jacob's Cavern. Folder 2 of 3., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, a drawing, and correspondence dealing with Jacob's Cavern and the history of elephants. (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Jacob's Cavern. Folder 3 of 3., Contains journal articles about Jacob's Cavern. (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Jacob's Cavern: Bone Correspondence., Contains letters about the decorated bone found in Jacob's Cavern and the resulting controversy. (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Joke book letters. Contains correspondence to and from Vance Randolph related to Randolph's book Hot Springs and Hell., Correspondents include: Robert Yoder, Woman's Day, Richard Dorson, Columbia University Press, Herbert Halpert, Kenneth Goldstein (Folklore Associates), Carl Withers, and Gershon Legman. (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Sam Leath., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes about Sam Leath, an Ozarks collector and explorer. (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Lecture notes taken by Vance Randolph (Photocopy)., Contains the photocopy of a notebook with Vance Randolph's handwritten notes on G. Stanley Hall's 1914-15 lectures at Clark University in Worcester, Massachusetts, on "The Psychology of Christianity." (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Lecture notes taken by Vance Randolph (Original)., Contains the original notebook photocopied in Folder 80. (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Locusts from the city., Contains newspaper clippings and handwritten notes dealing with the impact of tourists from the city on the Ozarks. (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Walter Clare Martin., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed and handwritten notes, dealing with the bow hunter Walter Clare Martin. (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - The Master's desk., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed notes dealing with the poet Edgar Lee Masters. (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Medicine show., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed notes dealing with medicine shows. (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - The Menace., Contains newspaper clippings and reprints of journal articles, and typed notes dealing with the Aurora, Missouri, newspaper The Menace. (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - The Mollyjoggers., Contains newspaper clippings, and typed notes dealing with fraternal organizations. (Box 7, Folder 87)